All right, בוקר טוב. Boker Tov. So today's דף Daf is פ"ו,
Peh-Vav, and we pick up with
החלונות ועובי החומה. Hachalonot Ve-ovi Hachoma. And the משנה Mishna spoke about
what happens if a limb from the קרבן פסח Korban Pesach goes
outside of its zone, the zone focusing on ירושלים, Yerushalayim, although we
had learned the day before that it also includes leaving the חבורה,
Chabura, the group that eats it, and that you have to take
off the part that's פסול, Pasul, but of course it's a problem
because it's all on a bone and how do you manage that?
And then the end of the משנה, Mishna, which we're focusing on,
talked about the doorway and whether in the doorway is considered to
be inside the city or outside the city and what about the
space where the actual door itself closes.
Now, I did want to point out, and then it speaks that
the windows and the thickness of the wall are all considered in
the city. So while in the doorway, from the point of the
door outwards, is considered outside of the city obviously,
somewhat interestingly the same thickness of the wall could be considered in
the city when you're not in the doorway but you're in a
window or you're on the top of the wall. So it's not
all the thickness of the wall's not all the same, it depends
whether again where exactly you are. Once you're outside the door, that
already defines you as being outside. Now, I did want to point
out that רמב"ם Rambam reads this משנה Mishna in a very interesting
way, maybe not, well, based on the גמרא Gemara it's interesting, and
רש"י Rashi says what we're talking here is about the walls around
ירושלים Yerushalayim and when are you outside of ירושלים, Yerushalayim, so if
you take a קרבן, Korban, any קרבן Korban out of ירושלים, Yerushalayim,
any קדשים קלים, Kodshim Kalim, it becomes invalid. What's the story about
the walls? What's the story about the doorway, the window, the top
of the wall? רמב"ם Rambam says we're talking specifically about קרבן פסח
Korban Pesach and we're talking about the fact in any given house,
when is it considered that you've taken it out of the בית?
Bayit? Because it says, right, לא תוציא מן הבשר מן הבית חוצה.
Lo Totzi Min HaBasar Min HaBayit Chutza. So when is it outside
of the house? What if you're eating it in a window? What
if it's on the top of the, well I don't know how
you'd have a wall without a roof, but okay, you had some
top of wall without a roof on top of it and you
were on the thickness of the wall? What if you were in
the doorway? So the רמב"ם Rambam says it's talking specifically about the
house of the קרבן פסח, Korban Pesach, that connects to an issue
that came up the other day, which was when we redefine or
when we say that the prohibition is not about a house only,
it's about taking out of the group, is it also about taking
out of a house? Does the idea of a physical house also
matter or is it just about the group? So רמב"ם Rambam clearly
understands that the physical house also matters and therefore that's how he
reads this משנה Mishna about what's defined as the house. But as
we'll see in the גמרא, Gemara, the גמרא Gemara seems to read
it very much about ירושלים, Yerushalayim, which is where רש"י Rashi was
coming from.
Let's take a look at the גמרא. Gemara. החלונות ועובי החומה, Hachalonot
Ve-ovi Hachoma, the windows and the thickness of the wall are like
they're on the inside. אמר רב, Amar Rav, says רב, Rav, גגין
ועליות לא נתקדשו, Gagin Ve-aliyot Lo Niskadshu,
that the rooftops and the second stories were not sanctified. So
the very language of sanctified means ירושלים, Yerushalayim, they don't have the
קדושה Kedusha of ירושלים Yerushalayim itself. And here we have an interesting
question, which is that all of ירושלים Yerushalayim is a place where
you eat קדשים קלים, Kodshim Kalim, right? You eat the sacrifices like
the שלמים Shlamim that can be eaten in
ירושלים. Yerushalayim. Now, where can you eat those sacrifices? Can you eat
them, you have to eat them on the ground? Can you eat
them sitting on a rooftop?
Are those also have the same קדושה Kedusha of ירושלים? Yerushalayim? Now,
it's a little bit
of
a strange thing to think, what? They don't have the קדושה Kedusha
of ירושלים Yerushalayim just because you're on a rooftop?
So I heard probably once many many years ago from Aharon Lichtenstein
I think the best פשט Pshat about this, which is we don't
mean in all regards, like if you look at certain discussions about
מעשר שני, Maaser Sheni,
we talk about you know there's גמרות Gemaros that talk about eating
it you know in a tree or eating it you know off
of the ground and so on. But it's actually that you can
think of the קדושה Kedusha of ירושלים Yerushalayim in two ways. One
is an extension of the בית המקדש. Beis HaMikdash. And as an
extension of the בית המקדש, Beis HaMikdash, we know the principle, we
saw it once before when we talked about if you remember the
כהנים Kohanim walking around in the blood, the idea of touching the
floor, that the כהנים Kohanim go barefoot, their feet have to touch
the floor, the very floor of the בית המקדש Beis HaMikdash is
sanctified and therefore you have to be like in contact with it.
From that perspective, when we talk about eating קרבנות Korbanot where we're
seeing ירושלים Yerushalayim as a like as an extension of the בית
המקדש, Beis HaMikdash, there's קדשי קדשים Kodesh Kodashim and there's קדשים קלים,
Kodshim Kalim, but it's all about eating קרבנות, Korbanot, just eating it
a little bit more distant from the בית המקדש, Beis HaMikdash, there
the discussion is, does it apply to things that are not actually
ground level, would it even apply to roofs and to second stories,
because as in the בית המקדש Beis HaMikdash we assume it's the
floor that's
קדוש Kadosh and not you
can't eat קדשי קדשים. Kodesh Kodashim.
Well, that's it—becomes an interesting question, right? I mean, the, you know,
the בית המקדש Beis HaMikdash didn't have a dirt floor either, but
like, can you not eat on a rug? You know, exactly where
to draw the line is not clear. But at least conceptually, that's
our starting point. Whereas in regards other areas when we generally think
of the קדושה Kedusha of ירושלים, Yerushalayim, which is not necessarily just
in terms of like the קדשים Kodshim perspective of the בית המקדש,
Beis HaMikdash, maybe the proximity, the suburbs of the בית המקדש, Beis
HaMikdash, but not like an extended בית המקדש. Beis HaMikdash. So from
that perspective, for example, right, there's a מצוה mitzvah that says ושמחתם
לפני ה׳ אלהיכם, Vesamachtem lifnei Hashem Elokeicha, right, ולקחתם לכם ביום הראשון
פרי עץ הדר, Ulekachtem lachem bayom harishon pri etz hadar, ושמחתם לפני
ה׳, usmachtem lifnei Hashem,
what's the פסוק? pasuk? אלהיכם שבעת ימים. Elokeicha shivat yamim. So the
חז״ל Chazal understand there's a מצוה mitzvah to take the לולב lulav
seven days in ירושלים. Yerushalayim. Okay, all seven days, a מצוה דאורייתא,
mitzvah d'Oraisa, not just דרבנן. d'Rabbanan. So that's only on the floor?
You couldn't do it on a second story? There it's not about
it being an extension of the בית המקדש. Beis HaMikdash. And so
that actually is helpful in understanding this idea that perhaps the—you know,
only the floor was sanctified for—specifically from the perspective of eating קרבנות.
korbanos. Yeah.
When the כהן kohen walks up the ramp in the מזבח, Mizbeach,
he's not on the floor.
Right,
but he's— That
counts as the floor.
Yeah, I mean, it's—I mean, again, it's—that's, you know, it's a good
point. I mean, how much it's a permanent part of the fixture
and of the structure. You know, I mean, the גמרא Gemara talks
about—when the גמרא Gemara part talked about the blood, remember it says
that they sort of jumped from pillar to pillar? So, you know,
there are things that are seen as part of the structure, yeah,
exactly.
The ramp was an actual— It's a good point.
It's a very good point.
Yeah, especially where there is no below
it, meaning, like, there's no second story. All right, it's a—it's a
very good point, you know, exactly what—where—what qualifies. All right, let's take
a look. גגין ועליות לא נתקדשו. Gagin va'aliyot lo nitkadshu. איני, Eini,
is that really true? ואמר רב משום רבי
חייא V'amar Rav mishum Rabi Chiya כזיתא פסחא והלילא פקע איגרא—meaning, k'zayita
Pischa v'Hallel paka igra you know, if everybody's only getting a כזית,
k'zayit, it means that there's a lot of people eating one קרבן.
korban. So it's an image, first of all, it rhymes a little,
and it's also an image of like a house that's packed with
people and everybody just gets a כזית k'zayit of the קרבן פסח
korban Pesach והלילא v'Hallel and they're singing the הלל, Hallel, פקע איגרא,
paka igra, and it bursts through the rooftops, like, you know, this
image, like the singing and the joy and it's so amazing, the
power of when they would eat their פסח Pesach and sing the
הלל. Hallel. But you also notice it rhymes, right? כזיתא פסחא הלל
פקע איגרא. K'zayita Pischa Hallel paka igra.
Okay, anyway, so מאי לאו—so mai lav that's a lovely little statement—does
that not show you דאכלי באיגרא? d'achli b'igra? They must be eating
on the rooftop if it's bursting through the rooftops. They say opposite,
they're bursting through because they ate up everything, but it takes it
literally. So you see they're eating the קרבן פסח korban Pesach on
the rooftop, ואמרי באיגרא v'amri b'igra
and they're saying the הלל Hallel on the rooftop. לא, Lo, not
necessarily, דאכלי בארעא ואמרי באיגרא. d'achli b'ara v'amri b'igra. They're eating on
the ground and then—it doesn't just say also like the song burst
through the rooftops—but they after they finish eating, then they go up
to the roof to say the הלל. Hallel. Okay, איני, eini, is
that really true? Again, this question that you have to
eat—והתנן, v'ha tenan, do we—we teach in a משנה Mishnah אין מפטירין
אחר הפסח אפיקומן. ein maftirin achar hapesach afikoman. You can't have an
אפיקומן afikoman after the פסח. Pesach. אפיקומן Afikoman is not what we
call the אפיקומן. afikoman. אפיקומן Afikoman in the sense of the משנה,
Mishnah, it's a Greek word, it actually means some type of a
dessert, some type of a thing you would eat, you know, at
the end of a meal to cleanse your palette, and you can't
do that after the פסח. Pesach. Now the חז״ל Chazal did
not—at least the—the Babylonian Talmud didn't understand the—the Greek derivation of the
word, so they had different speculations on what the word אפיקומן afikoman
meant.
ואמר רב, V'amar Rav, so רב Rav says שלא יעקרו מחבורה לחבורה.
shelo ya'akru mechabura l'chabura. That what this אפיקומן afikoman means is it
means that after you're done with the קרבן פסח, korban Pesach, you—even
if you're done eating, you shouldn't leave your group and go to
another group. We already learned you can't take the פסח Pesach from
one group to another. But even after you're done eating, don't go
ahead and go sing the הלל Hallel with another group. Sounds like
they're having חבורה הוי. chabura hava. Yeah, exactly, sounds like they're having
more fun next door, I'm going to join their הלל Hallel next
door.
That's actually what אפיקומן afikoman means in Greek—that they went to parties
afterwards, bar hops.
Literally אפיקומן afikoman means that? I thought it meant like a palette
cleanser, no? I
think—Whatever, save the phenomenon of going from house to
house—And partake in certain activities—Oh really? Which the חכמים Chachamim would
not—Yes, that I can imagine. Interesting. Thank you. Okay, well then I
stand corrected.
So—of course רב Rav came from ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael originally, so—so
it might be exactly the meaning. Anyway, so they're saying, so you
can't leave after you're eating to go to a different place to
say הלל. Hallel. So how'd they leave the ground and go to
the rooftop to say הלל? Hallel? So the גמרא Gemara says לא
קשיא, lo kashya, it's not difficult, כאן בשעת אכילה כאן שלא בשעת
אכילה. kan b'sha'at achila kan shelo b'sha'at achila. It matters whether it
is at the time of eating, then you're not allowed to join
another group, even if you're done eating because that seems like you're
joining them for the eating. But if it's not the time of
eating and everybody's done eating, then you're allowed to go—you are allowed
to go somewhere else, which is interesting because you would have said
the difference here is you didn't join another group, part of the
group just moved to the rooftop, it's not like they joined another—
another group. You could have said that's very different than actively joining
another group. But the גמרא's Gemara distinction is is that everybody is
done eating, so therefore there is more latitude of moving around afterwards.
Yeah and you'd say הלל Hallel on your rooftop. So now we're
still back to our question though about whether the rooftops were sanctified.
תשמע Tashma come and hear. What? Isn't that by a question how
could they eat it?
No, they didn't eat at the rooftops. After they ate, they went
to say הלל Hallel at the rooftops, that's the answer.
Well what is the... שדעת שי... Sheda'at she...
that you can move to do some... you can go to... you
can move from your location of eating after everybody is done eating.
So that's why they were allowed to move to the rooftop. תשמע
Tashma come and hear, אבא שאול אומר: Abba Shaul Omer: עלית בית
קדשי קדשים, Aliyat Beit Kodesh Kadashim, the... the עליה aliya you know
the second story above the קדשי קדשים... Kodesh Kadashim... חמורה מבית קדשי
קדשים chamura mibeit kodesh kadashim is even more stringent in like its
holiness or the you know the way it was treated than the
actual Holy of Holies itself. You see this was the דף daf
that should have been learning yesterday on יום כיפור Yom Kippur and
here it actually has a direct allusion or a direct... not even
more than allusion... reference to יום כיפור. Yom Kippur. שבית קדשי קדשים
כהן גדול נכנס לו פעם אחת בשנה Shebeit Kodesh Kadashim Kohen Gadol
nichnas lo pa'am achas bashana that the Holy of Holies the כהן
גדול Kohen Gadol would go once in a year on יום כיפור.
Yom Kippur. Okay. ועלית בית קדשי קדשים Ve'aliyat Beit Kodesh Kadashim and
the the chamber above it אין נכנסים לה אלא פעם אחת בשבוע
ein nichnasim la ela pa'am achat beshavua you only go in once
every seven years. ואמרי לה פעמיים בשבוע Ve'amri la pa'amayim beshavua maybe
twice every seven years. ואמרי לה פעם אחת ביובל Ve'amri la pa'am
achas beyovel but some say once every fifty years. לדע מה היא
צריכה Leda ma hi tzericha to know if it needs any repairs.
So...
this means it's more חמור. chamur.
Right, it sounds just like that they had no need to go
there except for a functional occasional time. Anyway, the... by the way
I'll tell you a nice מהרש"א Maharsha because it also ties into
סוכות Sukkot where he says the גמרא Gemara you know talks about
how famous... a famous מדרש midrash by the סוכה sukkah that says
how do you know a סוכה sukkah has to be minimally ten
טפחים tefachim high and it says because you know the divine presence
the שכינה Shechina never came lower than ten טפחים tefachim even when
it says God came down on הר סיני Har Sinai it's always
like above ten טפחים tefachim and person never went within ten טפחים
tefachim of the heavens. This idea you know the impossibility of... of...
like of actual contact between the human and the divine. Like it's
sort of like that... What?
That מדרש midrash is incredible.
I know. It's sort of like that... you know the Sistine Chapel
you know God and... and Adam but their fingers aren't touching. You
know the impossibility of actually having contact even when God comes down
on הר סיני. Har Sinai. So anyway, so the relevance of this
to the סוכה sukkah since the סוכה sukkah you know is about
the ענני כבוד Ananei Kavod and about the divine presence coming down
but ultimately the ענני כבוד Ananei Kavod have to be higher than
ten טפחים tefachim so the סוכה sukkah has to be at least
ten טפחים tefachim to symbolize you know that we're not... that God
isn't coming down below that. So the מהרש"א Maharsha says so if
you think about the קדשי קדשים Kodesh Kadashim which is where the
divine presence is, so the divine presence can't fully be down because
it can't go lower than ten טפחים. tefachim. So the room above
it is... is more of the divine presence than the room below
it. Yes and... yeah he says that here. Anyway, alright, so obviously
this could just be because they didn't need to go into it
but let's see. But the... but the point is that since it
call... this seems to suggest minimally that the room above it had
the קדושה kedusha of the מקדש Mikdash so you see a second
story has the קדושה kedusha it's not just the ground level. So
the גמרא Gemara says: אמר רב יוסף מהיכא ניקו ונסבי אינשי? Amar
Rav Yosef meheicha neiku unasei inshi? Is a person going to come
and ask a question from the היכל? Heichal? From the... from the
בית המקדש Beit HaMikdash itself or the actual היכל? Heichal? שאני היכל
דכתיב, Shani Heichal dichtiv, by the היכל Heichal it says: ויתן דוד
לשלמה בנו את תבנית האולם Vayiten David l'Shlomo b'no et tavnit ha'ulam
David gave to Shlomo his son the... the... plans you know the...
the... blueprints right for the אולם Ulam which is the area before
the היכל. Heichal. ואת בתיו Ve'et batav and its chambers, ואת גנזכיו
ve'et ganzachav which was presumably the treasure chambers, ועליותיו ve'aliyotav and the
second story chambers. וחדריו הפנימיים Vechadarav hapnimiyim and its rooms the inner
ones, בית הכפורת Beit Hakapporet and even the קדשי קדשים Kodesh Kadashim
where the ארון Aaron is. So it... so this was
part of the plans. וכתיב Vechativ and it says הכל בכתב מיד
ה' עלי השכיל, Hakol bichtav miyad Hashem alai hiskil, everything was from
the... from... straight from the you know straight from God. God gave
me the blueprints. So somehow because the היכל Heichal is part of
the divinely given blueprints of the בית המקדש Beit HaMikdash and the
second chambers are part of that clearly they were sanctified as well
but that's not necessarily relevant for the question of ירושלים Yerushalayim and
the status of rooftops and chambers there. תש... Tash...
yeah that's a quote from דברי הימים Divrei HaYamim that's a strange
place to derive... derive הלכה? halacha?
Yeah again it's not technically deriving הלכה, halacha, it's... the גמרא Gemara
actually quotes that פסוק pasuk a good deal. It's... right it's reflecting
a reality that it all came... it's evidence that it all came
from God. תשמע Tashma come and hear, הלישכות הבנויות בקודש Halishkot habanuyot
bakodesh
and now we're bringing a proof from the בית המקדש Beit HaMikdash
itself but not exactly from the היכל. Heichal. So maybe the פסוק
pasuk there emphasized the היכל Heichal so maybe we feel it's still
acceptable to bring a proof from the larger בית
המקדש. Beit HaMikdash. the chambers that were built into in the sanctified
space ופתוחות לחול *uftuchos lachol*, but their doors opened into the non-sanctified
space, תוכן חול chol. *tochan chol*, וגגותיהם קודש kodesh. *vegaggoteihem kodesh*. Their
floor is חול chol. *chol* and their rooftops are קודש kodesh. *kodesh*
are are holy. What does that mean?
It means that it's physically, right.
By the way, just in case people forgot how the בית המקדש
Beis HaMikdash *Beis Hamikdash* looks like, let's just do a quick sketch
for some. Okay, this is the קודש kodesh הקדשים *Kodesh Hakodashim*, okay,
this is called the היכל Heichal *Heichal*, which is where you have
right the מנורה *Menorah*, the שולחן *Shulchan*, and the what is it?
Okay,
here is the מנורה *Menorah*, the שולחן *Shulchan*.
Okay, this is your אולם *Ulam*.
All of this is covered, right? And then around here you've got
your whole בית המקדש Beis HaMikdash? *Beis Hamikdash*, right, which is open
air and which is where the and which is where the what
do you call it the מזבח *Mizbeach* is and so on.
Your columns around that outer...
Oh yeah, this is walls but it's not doesn't have a roof
on it. Walls. Now let's say forget the היכל Heichal *Heichal*, the
actual edifice itself, and then this is הר הבית Har HaBayit *Har
Habayit*.
Let's say you've got here a chamber. Okay, and this chamber is
into קודש kodesh *kodesh*, it's inside right it's in this wall, but
the door to it is going to the חול chol, *chol*. Now
that's חול chol. *chol* הר הבית Har HaBayit, *Har Habayit*, but it's
not the קדושה kedusha *kedusha* of the בית המקדש Beis HaMikdash *Beis
Hamikdash*, right. So it says that the rooftops are קודש kodesh. *kodesh*
because it's part of the wall, the section it's in is actually
the קודש kodesh *kodesh* section, but the inside, the floor level, is
חול chol? *chol* because the use of it is from the outside
since it only has a door from the חול chol *chol*, it
doesn't have a door to the קודש kodesh *kodesh* as well. So
effectively this ground space is relevant to the area outside of it,
right, it's people that come from outside and go in, so it's
like their ground space, it's not used by the people here. But
the rooftop, which is not more accessible to one or the other,
technically physically that rooftop is in the קודש kodesh. *kodesh*. So it's...
How do you get to the rooftop?
It doesn't matter.
That's a good question. How would you... maybe there's a maybe there's
a ladder from inside. So that's a good point. So then also
it's accessible only to the people who came from outside. But nevertheless,
since it's not directly, you know, part of the space this connects
to the space outside, it's all flat and the rooftop therefore is
קודש kodesh *kodesh* and the floor is חול *chol*. Yes.
Didn't one of these chambers have a מקוה *Mikveh* in it which
would be really important that it's not...
Yeah, well but these are only ones that only have the door
on the outside. Okay. So that's the הלכה *halacha*. So let's...
and this is not for example the לשכת העצים *Lishkas Haeitzim*, the...
Right, right, that's what that's what, you know, that's what Charlie was
asking.
I mean, yeah, they have plenty of לשכות *lishkos* here that
were open to the קודש *kodesh*. Right.
But if you had a לשכה *lishka* that
only opened to the חול *chol*, okay, then it is the ground,
the floor, is like an extension of the floor outdoors where it
was open to it, it was only open to the חול *chol*.
What were in these chambers?
I don't know. Maybe they used it to sell various, you know,
animals or salt or whatever. So okay, so let's take a look.
And no rooftop?
There would be a roof in
that section of
the wall, right?
There would be a roof. Why would there be a roof? You
got a wall. Here's your wall of the בית המקדש Beis HaMikdash.
*Beis Hamikdash*. If this inside here is the בית המקדש Beis HaMikdash.
*Beis Hamikdash* proper and here you're coming from הר הבית Har HaBayit.
*Har Habayit*, if this is your wall and here's your door, okay,
so this chamber, right,
since it's accessible to you from the outside, right, even if it's
closed on the inside, right, so this chamber is שייך *shayach* to
the outside.
In six years we'll get there.
What?
Yeah, I thought you were saying in six years I'll learn how
to draw. Okay, anyway, so let's take a look. תא שמע Ta
shema,
*Tashma*, come and hear. הלשכות הבנויות
בקודש *Halishkot habnoyot bakodesh*...
I'm rereading the question. הלשכות הבנויות בקודש פתוחות לחול תוכן חול וגגותיהן
קודש *Halishkot habnoyot bakodesh uftuchos lachol tochan chol vegaggoteihem kodesh*. So you
see the roofs are קודש *kodesh*. At the end of the day
you have a rooftop that's קודש *kodesh*. And again we're assuming that
maybe before it was only the proof was only rejected because the
היכל Heichal *Heichal*. Here it's the actual בית המקדש Beit HaMikdash, *Beis
Hamikdash* itself. So you don't have the answer oh it's all from
God. So תרגמה רב חסדא בשגגותיהן שוין לקרקע עזרה Azarah, *targuma Rav
Chisda beshegaggoteihen shavin lekarka Azara*. No,
what we're talking about actually is a chamber that is built underground,
so the roof of the chamber is actually flat with the עזרה
Azarah, *Azara* itself. Do you understand the description here?
It's like it's recessed. What? It's recessed, right. I mean I guess
if you had a side view and this was the עזרה Azarah,
*Azara*, right, and here was your
מזבח *Mizbeach* and whatever, and this was your and this was your
הר הבית Har HaBayit, *Har Habayit*. Okay, so then basically you had
a chamber here. It makes sense because הר הבית Har HaBayit *Har
Habayit* is, you know, it's on the side. So your chamber is
like this.
Okay, so it's accessible
as you're walking up from the הר הבית Har HaBayit *Har Habayit*,
but the roof of
it is actually in the עזרה Azarah, *Azara*, it's... actually flat with
the עזרה Azarah itself.
In other words, the roof is actually the floor.
The roof, the roof of the chamber is the floor of the
עזרה, Azarah correct. Okay, so that's the answer. So therefore that's how
it could be קדש. Kodesh. So the גמרא Gemara says, where are
we, תשכח שוין לקרקע. tishkach shavin l'karka. אי הכי, Ei hachi,
if that's true, אימא סיפא, eima seifa, look at the end of
that, of that ברייתא, braita, actually it's a משנה, Mishna, I'm sorry.
בנויות בחול ופתוחות לקדש, benuyot b'chol u'ptuchot l'Kodesh, if it's the reverse,
that the chamber is built in the non-sanctified space, but it opens
up into the קדש, Kodesh, so the reverse is true. תוכן קדש,
Tochan Kodesh,
surprisingly, the inside is קדש Kodesh because it's used by the קדש.
Kodesh. That use defines it as קדש, Kodesh, וגגותיהן חול, v'gagoteihen chol,
and the roof is חול. Now why is that a problem? ואי
סלקא דעתך, V'ei salka da'atach, שגגותיהן שוין לקרקע עזרה, she'gagoteihen shavin l'karka
Azarah,
so if we're talking about the idea that these are, the roofs
are the floor of the עזרה, Azarah? so we're really talking about
underground chambers. הוו להו מחילות, Hevi lehu mechilot,
then basically what we're talking about is like tunnels. ואמר רבי יוחנן,
V'amar Rabbi Yochanan, מחילות לא נתקדשו, mechilot lo nitkadshu, and Rabbi Yochanan
teaches that the tunnels that ran under הר הבית Har HaBayit, and
under the בית המקדש Beit HaMikdash, were not sanctified.
Were not קדושת המקדש, kedushat haMikdash, right?
But קדושת הר הבית, kedushat Har HaBayit, maybe, fine. But okay, anyway,
so how could we say תוכן קדש, Tochan Kodesh, just 'cause they're
used by, by access by the בית bayit המקדש? HaMikdash, But if
we're talking about tunnels, tunnels are not קדש Kodesh according to Rabbi
Yochanan, so that can't be. So the גמרא Gemara says, no. כי
אמר רבי יוחנן, Ki amar Rabbi Yochanan, בפתוחות להר הבית. b'ptuchot l'Har
HaBayit. כי תניא ההיא, Ki tanya hahi, בפתוחות לעזרה. b'ptuchot l'Azarah. When
did Rabbi Yochanan say that they're not קדש? Kodesh? That's
the tunnels underneath הר הבית, that they don't have the קדושה kedusha.
of הר הבית. We're talking about tunnels that are accessed and are
underneath the עזרה, Azara. the actual בית bayis, המקדש itself. That would
have קדושה. kedusha So the גמרא Gemara says, now of course why
would we make these types of distinctions? One of the reasons is
that, one of the reasons you need tunnels is again about people
that become טמא. tamei. So if you want to get them off
of הר הבית, then they can go through a tunnel so, and
the tunnels aren't sanctified, so they don't have a problem of being
on הר הבית when they're טמא tamei if the tunnels weren't sanctified.
So that's for the tunnels
that ran, like the מחילות הכותל mechilot HaKotel tours you go to.
Exactly. והתניא, Vehatanya, didn't we teach a ברייתא, braita, רבי יהודה אומר,
Rabbi Yehuda omer,
מחילות מתחת ההיכל חול? mechilot mitachat HaHeichal chol? But one minute, but
we thought actually that the tunnels underneath even the היכל Heichal itself,
let alone, let alone the המקדש, even the היכל Heichal are not
sanctified.
כי תניא ההיא, Ki tanya hahi, שבפתוחות לחול. she'b'ptuchot l'chol. Fine. The
ones that the opening is to the חול. But we're saying that
what are the ones that are קדש? Kodesh? When the opening is
to the קדש. Kodesh. So basically the principle is, is that these
things are defined by where the entrance is. Of course, if they
have two entrances or exits, that's another question, but if their
fundamental access is through the חול, they're חול. Fundamental access is קדש,
Kodesh, is קדש. Kodesh. In order to get around the problem of
saying that rooftops are קדש, Kodesh, we're saying we're all talking about
about sort of underground chambers. How about then the issue that we're
saying some of those chambers are קדש, Kodesh, tunnels are קדש Kodesh
and we have other teachings that they're חול? So again, they're only
going to be קדש Kodesh if number one, they're opened into the
קדש, Kodesh, which is what we've been saying. It depends on where
they're open to. And number two, they're only קדש, Kodesh, only those
underneath the היכל Heichal, and the בית bayis, המקדש. Those of הר
הבית specifically
were left to be חול in order for access for the טמאים.
tmei'im. Okay, so now we still don't have a resolution whether the
rooftops are קדש Kodesh or not. Let's take a look. So the
גמרא Gemara says,
תא שמע, come and hear. גגו קדש. Gago Kodesh. So it says
that the,
let me just recheck what the reference to this is. גגו של
היכל,
Gago
shel Heichal, right.
The roof of the היכל Heichal is קדש. Kodesh. So it said
that the היכל Heichal was all roofed, it was, and its roof
was קדש. Kodesh. So you see that the rooftops are קדש. Kodesh.
Now of course this was the היכל, Heichal, we already had dismissed
that as evidence. Anyway, ותסברא, v'tisbara, does that make sense? והתניא, Vehatanya,
גגים הללו אינו אוכלים שם קדשי קדשים gagim halalu einu ochlim sham
kodshei kodashim ואין שוחטים שם קדשים קלים, v'ein shochtim sham kodashim kalim,
that you cannot use the rooftops
of the היכל Heichal and of the,
in order to שחט shacht קדשי קדשים kodshei kodashim or eat קדשים
קלים. kodashim kalim. So even eating קדשים קלים kodashim kalim you can't,
which means it doesn't even have the קדושה kedusha of, I'm sorry,
you can't שחט, shacht, excuse me. You can't eat קדשי קדשים kodshei
kodashim and you can't שחט shacht קדשים קלים. kodashim kalim. So you
see the rooftops of the היכל Heichal are not considered to have
the קדושה kedusha of the עזרה, Azara 'cause that's what you need
the עזרה Azarah, for. The עזרה Azarah? is the place is that
you can only, is the place that you can eat קדשי קדשים
kodshei kodashim and that you can שחט shacht קדשים קלים. kodashim kalim.
ואלא קשיא, V'ela kashya, so what do you do with that line
that גגו קדש, Gago Kodesh, that the roof is considered קדש Kodesh
if you're telling me it doesn't have the קדושה Kedushah of the
עזרה? Azarah, So אמר רב חמא בר גוריא, Amar Rav Chama bar
Guria, לאותן שתי אמות. l'otan shtei amot.
For the two אמות, amot, here do not mean literal
cubits themselves, but they actually mean the measuring sticks.
שתי אמות, Shtei amot, measuring sticks that they would have in the
בית המקדש. What does that mean? דתנן, Detnan, we taught in the
משנה, Mishna, שתי אמות היו בשושן הבירה. Shtei amot hayu be'Shushan HaBirah.
They had two measuring sticks in, this also doesn't mean literally שושן
הבירה, Shushan HaBirah, it means a special chamber that was called שושן
הבירה. Shushan HaBirah. אחת על. achat al. קרן מזרחית צפונית ואחת על
קרן מזרחית דרומית, keren mizrachit tzfoni'it ve'achat al keren mizrachit dromit,
one that they kept on the south, on the northeast corner and
one on the northwest corner, on the, on the southeast corner. זו
שעל קרן מזרחית צפונית, zu she'al keren mizrachit tzfoni'it, the one on
the northeast corner, היתה יתירה על של משה חצי אצבע, hayta yeteira
al shel Moshe chatzi etzba, was bigger than the official אמה amah
that we have through משה רבינו, Moshe Rabbeinu, you know the אמה
amah that they used in the מדבר midbar as it were, it
was bigger from it a half of a finger. So if you
think an אמה amah is six טפחים tefachim which is 24 fingers,
so a half of a finger bigger is about 2% bigger. וזו
שעל קרן מזרחית דרומית, ve'zu she'al keren mizrachit dromit,
and the one on the southeast corner, היתה יתירה עליה חצי אצבע,
hayta yeteira aleha chatzi etzba, was another half of a finger bigger
than it. So it was 4% bigger than the official one of
משה. Moshe. נמצאת יתירה על של משה אצבע, nimtzat yeteira al shel
Moshe etzba, was one finger bigger than that of משה. Moshe. ולמה
היו אחת גדולה ואחת קטנה? ve'lama hayu achat gedola ve'achat ketana? Why
was there one big and one small? You could also ask why
was any of them bigger than the official one of משה? Moshe?
שהיו אומנים נוטלין בקטנה ומחזירין בגדולה, she'hayu umnim notlin be'ketana u'machzirin be'gedola,
because when the craftsmen
would take the materials from the בית המקדש, they would, the idea
would be you didn't want them, you wanted them to be very
careful about not wasting the material from the בית המקדש, you also
didn't want them to be lining their pockets at all. So what
you would do is you would measure out what they would, what
you would give them with the official אמה, amah, and you would
measure out what they gave back with the bigger אמה. amah. So
it actually means that they have to, right, that they have to
give back more, if they use anything they'd have to give back
more than they took, which is a way of making sure that
they're careful not to take any excess. Of course, what happens if
they are very careful, then they're going to lose out a little
bit because they're going to have to make up the difference. What?
Right, so I guess if everybody knows the system, but it's true,
it's a very good point. You got a פסוק pasuk of אבן
ואבן. evven va'evven.
These are not כהנים. kohanim. Right, right, these are not כהנים, kohanim,
these are people that were hired to do the craftswork. Do you
remember, right, even owning, you know, different measures?
That's a very good question. I don't know about how satisfied, how
he feels about that פסוק. pasuk.
It's a good point. Dov makes the excellent point that there's just
a prohibition of owning even different measures that are not exactly accurate.
I mean, I guess if it explicitly was labeled אמה amah plus
a finger, אמה amah plus a half-finger, but then of course... anyway,
today it's a very funny system. I never really understood it. I
didn't understand it anyway because what did you do? You made a
big stone or whatever, you know, whatever you made out of it,
then how would you measure, you'd have to measure the object made
and measure the remainder, but those things aren't all given for like
linear measurements of an אמה. amah. You know, I mean especially if
you took gold and you made some type of a platter or
a bowl, you're not going to use an אמה amah stick to
measure how much gold was used in that. I never really understood
this, but Dov also the point about the different measuring sticks is
a very good one. שהיו אומנים נוטלין בקטנה ומחזירין בגדולה, she'hayu umnim
notlin be'ketana u'machzirin be'gedola, why did they do this? שהיו אומנים נוטלין
בקטנה ומחזירין בגדולה כדי שלא יבואו לידי מעילה, she'hayu umnim notlin be'ketana
u'machzirin be'gedola kedei she'lo yavo'u lidei me'ila,
that they would take, they'd be measured out the material given to
them in a small one and give it back in a big
one. We are about to say. In order that they should not
come to misuse of הקדש Hekdesh materials. ותרתי למה לי? ve'tarti lama
li? So why do you need two? אחת לכסף וזהב ואחת לבניינא.
achat le'kesef ve'zahav ve'achat le'vinyana.
One for measuring out gold and silver, so you don't want to
make it too difficult for them so it's only a 2% increase
in the, you know, of the difference of what you'll give and
what you'll take back, as opposed to the one for the, like
the stones and the wood, there we can be a little, it's
not so expensive, 4%. I gotta tell you, 2% of gold and
silver, I don't know how anybody's making a profit here. Anyway, I
guess they adjusted their prices accordingly.
So they had three, they
had like
משה, Moshe's, right, these two. Exactly. Anyway, what does all this have
to do with anything? So the ברייתא braita teaches, it says that
the top of the היכל, Heichal the roof of the היכל Heichal
is קודש. Again, interesting the גמרא Gemara didn't say the answer it
said before. The היכל Heichal we get from God, you know, direct,
direct, maybe there was only about second stories, this is about the
rooftop, I don't know. And the answer was, yeah, it's not really
קודש. You can't really use the rooftop of the היכל like the
עזרה. Azarah You can't שחט shecht קרבנות, korbanos, you can't eat קדשי
קדשים kadshei kadashim on it. All it means it's קודש is that
they had some קודש use for it, like they would store the
sticks or whatever, the measuring sticks they would store it there. So
it doesn't really mean קודש. Which of the sticks on the rooftop?
Yeah, it's even stranger, I know, especially here because it says something
like that. I mean it's strange because here it says it was
actually in different corners. If you take a look at תוספות, Tosafot,
לא נצרכה אלא לאותן שתי אמות, lo nitzrecha ela le'otan shtei amot,
תוספות Tosafot says לא בא למימר דאותן שתי אמות היו מונחות בגגו
של היכל. lo ba le'meimar de'otan shtei amot hayu munachot be'gagga shel
Heichal.
He says first of all they weren't on the rooftop. דהשער מזרחי
שעליו שושן הבירה, de'hasha'ar mizrachi she'alav Shushan HaBira, שושן הבירה Shushan HaBira
was a, I didn't describe this, it was a like a, you
know, a carving of the city of שושן, Shushan, and it was
over the eastern gate of the מקדש, Mikdash, okay? דהשער מזרחי שעליו
שושן הבירה צורה אחת משערי עזרה היא. de'hasha'ar mizrachi she'alav Shushan HaBira
tzura achat mi'sha'arei Azara hi.
So that was one of the gates of the עזרה Azarah and
therefore it's, this is not, when it says it was in that,
it was not on the rooftop, it was in that gate היתה.
hayata. אלא הכי קאמר, ella hachi ka'amar, כמו שאותן שערי ke'mo she'otan
sha'arei was over the eastern gate of the מקדש. Mikdash. Okay? דהשם
יתברך Dehashem Yisborach tells the נביא Navi צורה אחת משערי העזרה היא.
Tzurah achas mishaarei haazarah hi. So that was one of the gates
of the עזרה, Azarah, and therefore this is not when it was
in that, it was not on the rooftop, it was in that
gate היה. hayah. אלא הכי קאמר, Ela hachi kaamar, כמו שאותן שערי
מזרח היה kmo sheosan shaarei mizrach hayah היה מקודש להניח שם כלי
קודש hayah mekudash lehaniach sham klei kodesh in the same way that
those gates were sanctified to put in it these vessels like the
like the measuring sticks. כמו כן גגו היכל קודש kmo chen gago
heichal kodesh דקאמר dekamar when it says that the roof was קודש
it means להצניע שם כלי קודש lehatznia sham klei kodesh to put
the vessels. Now then we got another problem. He says ולא שהיו
כלי קודש צריכים מקום מקודש, vlo shehayu klei kodesh tzrichim makom mekudash,
who said you have to keep the כלי קודש klei kodesh in
a holy place? Maybe you could keep them, who said they had
to be kept in the עזרה? Azarah, כדמוכח בכמה דוכתא. kedemochach bekama
duchsah. אלא הכא קדושה אית להו הניחם שם. ela hacha kedushah is
lehu anicham sham.
So you didn't really so it means yeah they were holy enough
to put them there but you didn't really need a holy place
to put this. So then what does it even mean? I don't
I don't even really understand. It says first of all these sticks
weren't kept on the rooftops, they were kept in a gate, and
number one and number two you don't even need the answer they
were sanctified enough to keep the vessels there but you don't need
sanctified space to keep the vessels there. So it really means it's
clearly לאו דווקא. lav davka. When it says it was קודש it
meant that was the place we kept the vessels but it doesn't
really mean it was קודש. So this question whether the rooftops were
קודש or not, you know, we have seen to have a clear
statement at least that the rooftops of the היכל did not have
the קדושה kedusha, of the עזרה, Azarah but somehow they have yet
to resolve it by ירושלים. Yerushalayim. So let's finish up the גמרא.
Gemara. It says like this. תנן החלונות ועובי החומה כלפנים. tnan hachalonos
veovi hachomah kifenim. So we have says that the windows and the
top of the walls, the thickness of the wall, like the inside.
So now we're still trying to prove the question. What's the story
about off the ground in ירושלים? Yerushalayim? בשלמא חלונות משכחת לה דשויה
לקרקע. bishlama chalonos mishkachas lah deshaveih lekarka. So the windows, yeah you
could say like you said before, it was a building built into
the you know incline of ירושלים, Yerushalayim, and the rooftop is the
floor of the you know is parallel to the floor, the rooftop
of the house is parallel to the floor. That's how we could
discuss it being having קדושת ירושלים. kedushas Yerushalayim. The windows. What?
I'm sorry, windows. משכחת לה דשויה לקרקע עזרה. mishkachas lah deshaveih lekarka
azarah. How do you have that? First of all it's not עזרה
Azara and I think רש"י Rashi says it was לאו דווקא עזרה
lav davka azarah because we're talking about we're talking about what do
you call
it? We're talking about ירושלים Yerushalayim now. So yeah, so how would
you get a window שוה לקרקע עזרה? shaveh lekarka azarah?
You have the עזרה Azara. and then you have a window.
Yeah, I guess it's the same idea.
Corner, I
mean, I guess it's the same idea.
Unless you're talking about windows that are you know you look down
at the floor.
I mean, again, if you have a if you have essentially because
we're probably talking about ירושלים Yerushalayim now and רש"י Rashi says we're
לאו דווקא lav davka talking about the עזרה, Azara but if you've
got a house built into you know built into
the
incline, right, so you could I guess have a window, well, I
guess if this is the top of the incline and your house
is right at the top and this is the עזרה, then you
have your window of your house here, so I guess the top
of the window, or I guess you could also have it like
this, if the house was higher than and here's the the עזרה
let's say the floor of ירושלים Yerushalayim starting, right? And your window
is here, and your window, right, the window would be here, or
I know, I guess the whole bottom sill of the window, the
window is there but you're in the window,
you're equal with where the first floor of ירושלים Yerushalayim is.
Something like like that. Okay. So that makes sense. אלא עובי החומה
היכי משכחת לה? ela ovi hachomah heichi mishkachas lah? But the wall,
the whole point of a wall, right, we're not talking about the
wall of the house, we're talking about presumably the wall of the
city, right? So for the wall of the city, how does the
wall of the city, the top of the wall end with a
floor? What good is a wall that ends with the floor of
the city that it surrounds? It's gotta be go higher than the
floor of the city. So the גמרא Gemara says משכחת לה בבר
שורא. mishkachas lah bevar shura. No, you have it with a secondary
wall. דכתיב ויאבל חיל וחומה. dechsiv vayavel cheil vechomah.
The חיל cheil and the חומה chomah were made you know bereaved
by the destruction of ירושלים. Yerushalayim. ואמר רבי אחא ואיתימא רב חנינא
שורא ובר שורא. veamar Rabbi Acha veiseima Rav Chanina shura uvar shura.
We mean the main wall and the secondary wall. So apparently רש"י
Rashi describes that normally you'd often have I might be what they
call a retaining wall, I don't know what
the coach is talking about there, well, the
way רש"י Rashi explains it is you've got a wall here around
the city and then inside, this is the inner part of the
city, you have a lower wall like this. Okay, that's a that's
the way רש"י Rashi explains it. So if you envision again that
we're here on an on an angle, so if you've got you
know your outer wall is
like that, and then your inner wall, wait how does רש"י Rashi
explain it?
Something like that. חומה קטנה פנימית מחומה גדולה ושווה לקרקע גובה עזרה.
chomah ktanah penimis
mechomah gdolah veshavah lekarka govah azarah.
Yeah I guess, the inner
wall, oh yeah, so the whole outer wall is here and again,
let's say the floor of the city starts here, right? And then
the inner wall is like this.
Anyway, somehow could be that the outer wall, that by the time
you get, am I being clear? I don't think so.
Retaining wall, I think a retaining wall keeps in, keeps the surface
Something like that. Exactly what you have with the כותל. Kotel. The
top of the כותל Kotel is flush with הר הבית, basically with
where the כיפת הסלע Kippat HaSela
is.
So that's a retaining wall.
Okay, so basically saying that the wall, it's the wall around the
city, or but then the second wall that the retaining wall is
actually, top of it is flush at with the additional incline between
the two, go inside the two walls at
some aspect like it's a retaining wall. Okay.
So he's saying no, the פסוק pasuk is two walls, but it
just says it's a retaining wall. Okay.
So basically
what we have here is, first of all, it's fun that they're
talking about the היכל because, you know, it's really talking about the,
it seems like it's talking about the ירושלים Yerushalayim at this stage.
But what we have here is we don't have a conclusion, and
we have all this evidence that sounds like, you know, conflicting evidence,
but a lot of it, especially our משנה, Mishna, sounds like rooftops
and whatever aren't sanctified, and the גמרא Gemara translates it all to
say that we're talking about when they're flush with the ground level.
But when they're actually off the ground level, they might not be
sanctified and we don't know the answer. And it talks both about
the עזרה and presumably ירושלים, Yerushalayim, although it keeps on referring to
the עזרה. And this is a little bit of a challenge to
the רמב"ם Rambam who reads the whole משנה Mishna to be talking
about the house you're eating קרבן פסח Korban Pesach in, because all
of this discussion is about the ירושלים Yerushalayim and the עזרה and
קדושה, not just defining a location, but actually the question of what
was sanctified. Okay, let's now continue to the next
משנה. Mishna. Yes, Michael, like many questions in the גמרא, Gemara, it's
not resolved. שתי חבורות, Shtei chaburot, now we get more directly to
the issue of the two groups, שהיו אוכלים בבית אחד. shehayu ochlin
bebavit achat.
I mean or to the idea of going outside of the group.
You have two groups that were eating in one household. אלו הופכין
את פניהם הילך ואוכלים ואלו הופכין את פניהם הילך ואוכלים. Eilu hofchin
et pneihem heilach ve'ochlin ve'eilu hofchin et pneihem heilach ve'ochlin.
Each one turns away from the other one and eats in their
own space. Now, it sounds like that is a requirement. רש"י Rashi
says that this is telling you that that is allowed. We're going
to see in the גמרא Gemara that there's a debate
about whether you can divide a קרבן פסח Korban Pesach into two
groups. Once the פסח Pesach is being eaten in a group, you
can't leave from one group to the next and eat it in
another group. Can you start off saying we all joined together with
this sheep, but you guys go over to that side of the
house and you go to that side of the house and we'll
split the קרבן פסח Korban Pesach into two groups? Are we allowed
to do that from the very beginning? And the משנה Mishna is
saying you are allowed, so when it says each one turns away,
it means each one is allowed to turn away in order to,
you know, and it's not a problem. רמב"ם Rambam actually reads it
that you have to. רמב"ם Rambam says once you have to, for
the רמב"ם, Rambam, yes, part of the חידוש chiddush is you're allowed
to have two groups. But once you have two groups, so the
רמב"ם, Rambam, this whole idea of eating it in one בית is
that it's important to define clear boundary lines, make it clear what
the, sort of which is group A and which is group B.
So once you're splitting it, you have to make sure that you're
not facing one another and you don't make it sort of, you
know, confusing exactly where one group ends and the next group begins.
And there's an actual physical מחיצה. mechitza. Well, the רמב"ם Rambam also
discusses having a physical מחיצה. mechitza.
והקומקום מלפניו veha'kumkum melafaneu on top of the משניות, mishnayot, yes.
Yes, correct.
הופכין פניהם ואוכלים. hofchin pneihem ve'ochlin. How do
you know they're sharing the same קרבן korban as aren't you? You
don't. It doesn't say. It says they were אוכלים בבית אחד, ochlin
bebavit achat, so you're right, it could even be two separate קרבנות.
korbanot. And I think, I have to double check רמב"ם, Rambam, I
think רמב"ם Rambam even might read it that way as well. Okay,
right. רש"י Rashi says חדא חדה chada chada because of the גמרא.
Gemara. But for the רמב"ם, Rambam, so רש"י Rashi is saying it's
one פסח Pesach and it's allowed. If I remember correctly, רמב"ם Rambam
says that we're talking either one or two, but the point is
it's required. If you're going to eat it in two groups or
if you have two separate groups, then the boundary lines have to
be clear. Okay. והמיחם באמצע. ve'hamicham be'emtza. And you're allowed to, according
to the רמב"ם, Rambam, have a heating, the thing, the heating pot
of water in the middle. They use hot water to mix with
their wine, and that you're allowed to share and we're not afraid
that it'll confuse the boundary lines between the groups.
כשהשמש עומד למזוג. keshehazzamash omed limzog. Now when the שמש shamash attendant
gets up to mix the wine, which he's doing again from this
hot water thing. Now the thing, the problem is that he presumably
has to eat his פסח Pesach as well. He's a Jewish שמש.
shamash. So he's eating with one group. Now he have to go,
the other group is calling him over. So he has to make
it clear that he's not eating with group B, since he's actually
eating with group A. So what does he do? קופץ את פיו.
kofetz et piv. He keeps his mouth closed. ומחזיר פניו umachzir pnav
and keeps his face pointing to group A. So everybody in group
A can see that he is not sneaking in a little bit
of the food from group B. עד שמגיע אצל חבורתו ad shemmagi'a
etzel chaburato until he gets back to his group. So it's quite
interesting like, you know, why, you know what, everybody is watching him
and making sure but again, you know, sometimes we're concerned about that
about חשד chashad and people suspecting you and trying to be above
suspicion, but it also seems that this is part of the idea
of like the boundary lines and maintaining clear boundary lines. If you
have an attendant going from one group to the next, that's very
confusing in terms of are you really separate groups and which group
is he in and there's a whole idea of being clear boundary
lines so he has to be very clear when he's going to
the other group. Of course how am I going to
pour
Does he stir with his head turned?
Yeah, I don't know exactly how he manages all of
that. Okay. והכלה הופכת פניה ואוכלת ve-hakalah hofechet paneha ve-ochelet and if
a newly born, a new wife also turns her face and eats,
we'll see in the גמרא Gemara whether it means she's allowed to
or she must, how we effect the understanding. Let's look at the
גמרא. Gemara.
Shows men and women ate it.
Absolutely, oh yeah, they were eating together. Okay, exactly. רב משה Rav
Moshe has a תשובה teshuvah about weddings and he says what's all
this nonsense about eating separately, we always you know ate men and
women together in Europe. Right, okay, anyway so hold on I guess
this is about to do something to me. Okay. So מתניתין מני,
matnisin mani, who's our משנה? Mishnah? רבי יהודה היא, Rebbi Yehuda hi,
it's רבי יהודה. Rebbi Yehuda. And this is where רש״י Rashi is
getting it from, this idea that the point of the משנה Mishnah
is that one פסח pesach can be divided. דתניא, detanya, we learn
in a ברייתא, braisa, על הבתים אשר יאכלו אותו בהם, al habatim
asher yochlu oto bahem, you the פסח pesach can be eaten in
the houses that you will eat it in therein. So על הבתים,
al habatim, you
could eat on the roof?
All right, exactly. מלמד שהפסח נאכל, melamed shehapesach ne'echal, now the problem
is בתים batim plural. Okay now you could say every group eats
in their own house but we're reading it very literally that a
פסח pesach is eaten in houses, one
פסח. pesach. מלמד שהפסח נאכל בשתי חבורות, melamed shehapesach ne'echal bishtei chaburos,
you can take one פסח pesach and divide it into two houses,
two groups.
So wait, how do you see it from בתים batim plural?
יכול יהא האוכל אוכל בשתי מקומות, yachol yehei ha'ochel ochel bishtei mekomos,
maybe a person can eat in one group and then go over
to another group and eat, maybe particularly if the פסח pesach itself
is divided into two, you can start in one group and then
join the other group of the other half of the פסח? pesach?
תלמוד לומר בבית אחד יאכל, talmud lomar bevayis echad ye'achel, one house.
Now יאכל ye'achel literally means it, the פסח, pesach, would be eaten
in one house, but we're reading it יוכל, yochal, you have to
eat in one house. The פסח pesach can be divided into two,
but you have to eat in one. מכאן אמרו, mikan amru, here
they said, from here they said, השמש שאכל כזית בצד התנור, hashamash
she'achal kezayis betzad hatanur, you have the attendant and there he is
by the oven roasting the קרבן פסח. korban pesach. And as he's
roasting the קרבן פסח, korban pesach, he's tasting a little bit of
it. So he tastes a little bit of the פסח pesach as
he's roasting it. Now he's got a problem, he has now designated
his space for the קרבן פסח. korban pesach. And the interesting thing
here is that a חבורה chabura doesn't even have to be multiple
people, one person is a חבורה. chabura. You started eating in this
space, this is your space, you can't go to another space. Okay,
so I'm off in this little side room where the oven is,
the basic eating room is this room or whatever. What am I
going to do? I just tasted it in that little oven room,
I'm stuck. So what am I going to do? I'm not allowed
to eat in more than one place.
He has three חבורות. chaburos.
Right. So what does he do? אם פיקח הוא, im pikeiach hu,
so if I'm smart, ממלא כרסו ממנו. memale kerso mimenu.
I better eat up my fill or however much I'm entitled to
right here by the oven. Okay, because once they take the meat
and divide it up, I'm not going to be able to go
over there and eat. So I better eat my כזית kezayis or
whatever much I'm entitled to right here. ואם רצו בני חבורה לעשות
עמו טובה, ve'im ratzu benei chabura la'asos imo tovah, and if the
other members of the group wanted to be nice to
him, באין ויושבין צדו. ba'in veyoshvin tzido. דאי משייך, de'i mishayach, exactly.
דברי רבי
יהודה, divrei Rebbi Yehuda, that's what רבי יהודה Rebbi Yehuda says. So
you can't eat in more than one place and the interesting idea
is wherever you start eating, that's your place, even if the rest
of the חבורה chabura isn't there. רבי שמעון אומר, Rebbi Shimon omer,
רבי שמעון Rebbi Shimon says differently. על הבתים אשר יאכלו אותו בהם,
al habatim asher yochlu oto bahem, he says differently, in the houses
you will eat it
therein. מלמד שאוכל אוכל בשתי מקומות. melamed she'ochel ochel bishtei mekomos. אשר
יאכלו אותו בהם, asher yochlu oto bahem, you can eat in two
places, actually a person can go from one place to another. Okay.
יכול יהא נאכל בשתי חבורות, yachol yehei ne'echal bishtei chaburos, so he
says the exact opposite, רבי שמעון, Rebbi Shimon, maybe you can divide
the פסח pesach into two groups. תלמוד לומר בבית אחד יאכל, talmud
lomar bevayis echad ye'achel, so he's reading it much more literally, it
shall be eaten in one house. The פסח pesach is eaten in
one house. Now of course if the פסח pesach is eaten in
one house, how can you eat in two places? Right, so right
because I mean if you're eating in a second place the same
פסח, pesach, then you're taking it to another house. So רש״י Rashi
says, no,
you understand,
so רש״י Rashi says, so I'll read רש״י Rashi second line near
the end, כלומר עיקר תחילת אכילתו תהא בחבורה אחת, klomar ikar techilas
achilato tehei bechabura achat, ולא יחלק לשתי חבורות, velo yechalek lishtei chaburos,
you can't start by dividing it. אבל גברא אי בעי קאי הכא
ואזל ואכל הכא בלא קפיד, aval gavra i ba'ei kamei hacha ve'azal
ve'achal hacha belo kapeid,
so you can go eat. Presumably you can't eat in another חבורה,
chabura, but you can eat in another place. Okay. So we're not
allowed to divide the פסח pesach into two groups. We all have
to be the same group for the same קרבן, korban, but once
we all start off in this room eating together, I can go
to other rooms in the house. Maybe I can't actually leave the
house itself, that's a question about בית, right, you know what defines
בית, but maybe I can go to other places in the same
room. But the פסח pesach has to be eaten by one group.
But you can't eat in another, in an area where the other
group is eating, right?
Certainly you can't go to another group. Okay.
But there's
no other group of the same פסח, pesach, according to him there'd
only be another group of another פסח. pesach. Okay. במאי קמיפלגי, bemai
kamiflegi, what are they debating? רבי יהודה סבר יש אם למסורת, Rebbi
Yehuda savar yesh em lemasoret, רבי יהודה Rebbi Yehuda says we go
by the מסורת, masoret, now interestingly מסורת masoret actually means the way
it's written. So since it's written בבית אחד יאכל, bevayis echad ye'achel,
it could be read as יוכל, yochal, so he says that means
that one person can only eat in one place. רבי שמעון סבר
יש אם למקרא, Rebbi Shimon savar yesh em lemikra, we go the
way it's read. It's read יאכל. ye'achel. And therefore no, it's not
one person eats in one place, it's the פסח Pesach has to
be with one, one group. But you can eat, as long as
you don't go to another group, you can eat and you can
move your place. Okay, so now we're going to have some interesting
scenarios that plays out the difference. היו יושבין ונפסקה מחיצה ביניהם. Hayu
yoshvin venifsaka mechitza beneihem. The, these two groups, and רש״י Rashi says
two separate פסחים Pesachs because according to רבי שמעון Rebbi Shimon you
can't have two groups for one פסח. Pesach. So you have two
groups, two separate פסחים Pesachs in the same, in the same room.
Separate spaces in the same room. And then a מחיצה mechitza got
placed between them. Somebody decided they was going to be very פרום
frum and they put up a מחיצה mechitza between them. A מחיצה.
mechitza. Okay, לדברי האומר פסח נאכל בשתי חבורות, L'divrei ha'omer Pesach ne'echal
bishtei chaburot, so according to the idea that, that one פסח Pesach
can be eaten in two places, two חבורות, chaburot, I mean it's
anyway here it's two פסחים, Pesachs, doesn't matter, אוכלין, ochlin, you can
continue eating. So that's sort of obvious, it's just two פסחים Pesachs
anyway. לדברי האומר אין פסח נאכל בשתי חבורות, L'divrei ha'omer ein Pesach
ne'echal bishtei chaburot, but if you say it cannot be eaten in
two groups, אין אוכלין, ein ochlin, you, oh wait, I think I,
I think I jumped ahead. I think that רש״י Rashi says this
is one group. Let me, hold on, let me,
one minute. No, no, I'm sorry, I was jumping ahead to the
next one. Let's start again. It's one group eating the same קרבן
פסח. Korban Pesach. But we're not, you know, but there's a little
space between us. Yeah, maybe the men and women are separate and
somebody put up a מחיצה mechitza between them. But it's one group.
Let's try it again. Okay, היו יושבין ונפסקה. Hayu yoshvin venifsaka. One
group was sitting eating the פסח. Pesach. And then a מחיצה mechitza
got set up between two halves of the group. לדברי האומר פסח
נאכל בשתי חבורות, L'divrei ha'omer Pesach ne'echal bishtei chaburot, if the פסח
Pesach can be divided into two groups, אוכלין, ochlin, keep on eating.
לדברי האומר אין פסח נאכל בשתי חבורות, L'divrei ha'omer ein Pesach ne'echal
bishtei chaburot, according to רבי שמעון Rebbi Shimon that you can't divide
into two groups, the מחיצה mechitza effectively divides the groups, אין אוכלין,
ein ochlin, you can't continue eating. Now,
היו יושבין, Hayu yoshvin, let's say they were sitting separated by a
מחיצה. mechitza. This is what I was, I was jumping ahead to
this. This is that it was two separate פסחים Pesachs and you
were sitting separated by a מחיצה. mechitza. So it was two groups,
but it was two separate פסחים Pesachs and you were separated by
a מחיצה. mechitza. נסתלקה מחיצה ביניהם Nistalka mechitza beneihem and then somebody
took down the מחיצה. mechitza. Okay, what's the big deal? לדברי האומר
L'divrei ha'omer because now the problem is, is that does it become
like it's a new space for me? I was here and there
was a wall, and I was eating with my group, and you
were eating with your group behind on the other side of the
wall, and they were even different פסחים. Pesachs. The wall fell down.
Is it now like I'm eating in a new space? I didn't
get up and move, but now it's a space that has, you
know, that's bigger. The other case, the space was a subset. It
was a big space, it was divided, a subset is not a
new space. But when it's, when it's, when it's larger than the
original space, maybe it's now like I'm in a new space. So
now we're saying what happens, היו יושבין ונסתלקה מחיצה ביניהם, Hayu yoshvin
venistalka mechitza beneihem, לדברי האומר אוכל אוכל בשני מקומות, L'divrei ha'omer ochel
ochel bishnei mekomot, אוכלין. ochlin. So if you can eat in two
spaces, it's okay, it's a new space, but continue eating. לדברי האומר
אין אוכל אוכל בשני מקומות, L'divrei ha'omer ein ochel ochel bishnei mekomot,
if you can't eat in two spaces. Again, you didn't move at
all and you're with your חבורה. chaburah. You haven't moved from your
חבורה, chaburah, but it's a new space now. אין אוכלין, ein ochlin,
you can't continue to eat.
But why should the second space? What? Why is it
considered?
That's what the גמרא Gemara is going to say. The assumption is
that if it's a bigger space, even if you haven't moved, it's
a new space. יתיב רב כהנא וקפשיט ליה מפשט. Yativ Rav Kahana
veka pasheit lei mipashat. So רב כהנא Rav Kahana was sitting and
telling this over and he was taking this for granted. אמר ליה
רב אשי לרב כהנא, Amar lei Rav Ashi l'Rav Kahana, so רב
אשי Rav Ashi said to רב כהנא, Rav Kahana, איבעי לך איבעיא,
Itibai lach ibaya, why you taking this for granted? You should ask,
this should be a question. סילוק מחיצה ועשיית מחיצה, Siluk mechitza va'asiyat
mechitza, what happens if you remove a מחיצה mechitza or you put
up a מחיצה? mechitza? ני האוי כבי מקומות וכבי חבורות דמי או
לאו? Ni havei k'vei mekomot u'k'vei chaburot dami o lav? Does putting
up a מחיצה mechitza make one חבורה chaburah into two? Does taking
down a מחיצה mechitza make one space into a new space or
not? Take, so the גמרא Gemara actually says you shouldn't be so
obvious, it's actually a question. We can't take questions because we have
five minutes to finish the דף. daf.
But why isn't this building or destroying on יום טוב?
Yom Tov? Okay, that's a separate discussion which I can talk to
you about later. הכלה הופכת את פניה. Hakallah hofeches es panei'ha. Anyway,
it didn't say it was corrected that it was done, it says
that it happened. Okay, הכלה הופכת את פניה. Hakallah hofeches es panei'ha.
Now the bride turns her face away. מאי טעמא? Mai ta'ama? Why
is she turning her face away? Is she required? Is she allowed?
אמר רבי חייא בר אבא אמר רבי יוחנן, Amar Rebbi Chiya bar
Abba amar Rebbi Yochanan, משום שהיא בושה. mishum shehi bosha. She's embarrassed,
as she was to eat amongst, you know, she רש״י Rashi says
everybody's looking at her because, you know, she's newly married. הרי כדין.
harei kedin. I don't know, so somehow she was, you know, so
out of, she just, she just got married, she's still a little
bit shy to be eating with all with, you know, strange men
or something. So she's doing it. And part of the חידוש chiddush
is by the way, not maybe that she's, she's not, I don't
know, it sounds like it's not that she's required, that's what she's
doing. And the חידוש chiddush of the משנה Mishnah is she's allowed
to do it. That it's not considered like, oh, she's eating with
a different חבורה chaburah because she's turning around. You know, no, she's
in this חבורה, chaburah, she's allowed to be like, you know, to
be not chewing in front of other people and it not seem
like she's going to a different חבורה chaburah or a different space.
רב הונא בריה דרב נתן. Rav Huna brei d'Rav Nasan. Now we
have some interesting stories. רב הונא בריה דרב נתן איקלע לבי רב
נחמן בר יצחק. Rav Huna brei d'Rav Nasan ikla l'bei Rav Nachman
bar Yitzchak. So רב הונא Rav Huna came to the house of
רב נחמן בר יצחק. Rav Nachman bar Yitzchak. אמרו ליה, Amru lei,
they said to him, מה שמך, ma shimcha, what's your name? אמר
להו, Amar lohu, said to them, רב הונא. Rav Huna. Okay. אמרו
יתיב מר אפורייא, Amru yeisiv mar apuraya, sit here on the couch
because that was, you know, the respected place is that you recline
on a couch and you eat reclining on a couch, rather than
on a seat.
קבלה מינייהו, Kabla mineihu, he accepted from them.
סתם הדא. Stam hada. יתיב, Yasiv, he sat. יהבו ליה כסא, Yahavu
lei kasa, they gave him a cup of wine. קבליה בחד זימנא,
Kiblei be-chad zimna,
he accepted it even after being asked only once. All of this
was against the etiquette of the place. This whole point about this
is about how you have to know the etiquette of where you
are because every place has different etiquette. Everything he was doing was
seen as a faux pas, as we're about to find out. ושתייה
בתרי זימני, Ve-shasyei be-trei zimnei, and he drank it in two sips,
two gulps. ולא אהדר אפיה, Ve-lo ahadar apei, and when he drank
it he didn't turn his face
away, he did it in front of everyone. אמרו ליה, Amru lei,
so then they said to him, מאי טעמא קריתו לך רב הונא,
Mai ta'ama karisu lach Rav Huna, why do they call you רב
הונא? Rav Huna? אמר להו, Amar lehu, בעל שם אני, Ba'al shem
ani, that's my name. Actually, רש״י Rashi says that's my name, but
the מהרש״א Maharsha says no, בעל שם Ba'al Shem means a person
of status, means that he was telling them yeah, I'm a rabbi.
They didn't maybe believe that he was a rabbi; why is he
acting in such a
gauche
way?
Right. A rabbi? Right. He says yeah actually I have סמיכה, semicha,
I'm a rabbi. Really? So מאי טעמא כי אמרו לך נתיב אפורייא,
Mai ta'ama ki amru lach naseiv apuraya, why when we tell you
to sit on the couch, יתיבת, Yasivt, you sat? You're supposed to
say no, no, let me sit on the seat. אמר להו, Amar
lehu, he said to them, כל מה שיאמר לך בעל הבית עשה,
Kol ma she-yomar lecha ba'al ha-bayis asei, because there's a principle whatever
the בעל הבית ba'al ha-bayis tells you to do you should do.
Now there's an interesting last two words here, חוץ מצא, Chutz mi-tzei,
except for leave, which means what? You're not supposed to leave when
you're told to leave? It's like Jackie Mason has a great line,
he says
goyim leave without saying goodbye, Jews say goodbye, they never leave.
Anyway
the מהרש״א Maharsha has a nice explanation for this. He says once
the בעל הבית ba'al ha-bayis tells you to leave then he's no
longer your בעל הבית ba'al ha-bayis and then you don't do anything
he says. Anyway, but you still have to leave anyway. Okay. Now,
מאי טעמא כיהבו לך כסא, Mai ta'ama ki-yahavu lach kasa, why when
we gave you a cup of wine, a glass of wine, קבליה
בחד זימנא, kabulei be-chad zimna, you didn't refuse, you accepted? Again all
of that was a faux pas, you're supposed to say
no, no, don't give me whatever, you accepted it immediately. אמר להו,
Amar lehu, he said to them, מסרבין מקטן ואין מסרבין מגדול, mesarvin
mi-katan ve-ein mesarvin mi-gadol, because when somebody of lowly status asks you
something you're supposed to push off and refuse, it's a principle like
when the גבאי gabbai asks you for an honor you're supposed to
initially refuse although they say when they really need you don't refuse,
but anyway but if somebody of importance asks you you don't refuse.
So it's actually because I hold you in importance that's why I
accepted it. ומאי טעמא אשקיתיה בתרי זימני, U-mai ta'ama ashkiyatei be-trei zimnei,
why did you drink it in two sips, two gulps? אמר להו,
Amar lehu, דתניא, De-tanya, we learned in a ברייתא, braisa, השותה כוסו
בבת אחת, Ha-shoseh koso be-vas achas,
if you drink it all in one sip, הרי זה גרגרן, harei
zeh gargaran, you're considered like a glutton. שנים דרך ארץ, Shnayim derech
eretz, two gulps it's considered the normal way, acceptable. שלשה מגסי הרוח,
Shlosha mi-gasei ha-ruach,
three then you're very haughty, you drink it so daintily and so
slowly. ומאי טעמא לא אהדרת אפך, U-mai ta'ama lo ahadart apach, why
did you not turn your face away when you drank? It's like
chewing and drinking in front of people. אמר להו, Amar lehu, כלה
הופכת פניה. Kallah hofeches panei-ha.
So this is why we're bringing it in, because it's the כלה,
kallah, that's when we teach that it's דרך ארץ derech eretz to
turn away. But in normal cases it's not, even though in their
locale obviously that was the practice. תנן. Tnan. Now we taught in
a משנה, mishna, just one last רבי ישמעאל ברבי יוסי, Rabbi Yishmael
be-Rabbi Yosi, I'm sorry, תנן. Tnan. כלה הופכת פניה תנן, Kallah hofeches
panei-ha tnan, that's what we taught in the משנה. mishna. רבי ישמעאל
ברבי יוסי, Rabbi Yishmael be-Rabbi Yosi, איקלע לבי רבי שמעון ברבי יוסי
בן לקוניא. ikla le-bei Rabbi Shimon be-Rabbi Yosi ben Lakunya. So again
רבי ישמעאל Rabbi Yishmael came to the house of רבי שמעון. Rabbi
Shimon. יהבו ליה כסא, Yahavu lei kasa, they gave him a cup.
קבליה בחד זימנא, kabulei be-chad zimna, he accepted it immediately. ושתייה בבת
אחת, Ve-shasyei be-vas achas, and he drank it all at once. אמרו
ליה, Amru lei, they said to him, לא סבר ליה מר השותה
כוסו בבת אחת הרי זה גרגרן? Lo savar lei Mar ha-shoseh koso
be-vas achas ha-rei zeh gargaran? Don't you hold to the principle that
if you drink a cup all at once you're considered like a
glutton? אמר להו, Amar lehu, לא אמרו בהאי, Lo amru be-hai, they
didn't say this in this case because כוסך קטן, koscha katan, first
of all you got a small glass. Number two ויינך מתוק, ve-yeincha
matok, the wine is sweet so it's easy to drink a lot
quickly. וכרסי רחבה, U-charsi rechava,
and I've got a very wide stomach, so I'm allowed to drink
it in one gulp. Alright. Last
last thing. אמר רב הונא, Amar Rav Huna, bet you didn't think
we were going to finish the דף daf now. Look at that,
we got through the whole last thing in seven minutes. אמר רב
הונא, Amar Rav Huna, בני חבורה נכנסים בשלושה ויוצאים אפילו באחד. Bnei
chavura nichnasin bi-shlosha ve-yotzin afilu be-echad.
So רש״י Rashi says this is talking again about דרך ארץ derech
eretz halachas that if people hired a attendant, so until there are
three of them the attendant doesn't have to serve them because you
can't make him serve one or two people. But when they leave,
ויוצאים אפילו באחד, ve-yotzin afilu be-echad, even if only one of them
is left he still has to attend to them as they're breaking
up. אמר רבא, Amar Rava, והוא דעייל בעידנא דרגיל למיעל. Ve-hu de-ayeil
be-idna de-ragil le-me'al.
Number one, that's only if they got together at the normal time
that's normal and the guy is not staying later than the normal
time, so it's within normal working hours, in terms of what his
responsibility is to the group, this attendant. והוא דרגש ביה דיילא, Ve-hu
de-ragash bei dayala, and it's also that the דיילא dayala which is
a word for the attendant is sensitive and is aware
that they might break up and he might have to serve them
one by one. אמר רבינא, Amar Ravina, ונוטל שכר דמים, Ve-notel sechar
damim, but if he... Exactly if he actually does have to work
and serves them one by one and not as a group.
You say קדיש *Kaddish*?
You say קדיש *Kaddish*? No, if you want we can say קדיש
*Kaddish* here. He's not hearing. Okay, he's going to the קדיש *Kaddish*
in the שול *shul*. ונוטלין שכר דמין *v'notlin s'char damin*, they pay
for the you have to pay for his service if he's presumably
working overtime, וצריך אחרון להוסיף דמין *v'tzarich achron l'hosif damin*, and the
last guy who's making him really work overtime he has to even
he has to pay out of his own pocket. ולבסוף יחלוקו זה
עם זה *v'livsof yachloku ze im ze*, but we all rule that
I guess they all split the cost. תוספות *Tosfos* says by the
way this isn't talking about דרך ארץ *derech eretz*, it's talking about
the issue about if a group got together to eat the קרבן
פסח *korban pesach* and I said we're all the group, how many
of you guys do I have to wait for for me to
get started and that it's sort of talking in the context of
waiting for other people to get started in your eating of the
קרבן פסח *korban pesach*. Like three people? הדרן עלך כפי צאן *hadran
alach kefei tzon*. According to that you need three people. Do we
still have a מנין *minyan*? We do. We still have a מנין
*minyan*. Okay, does anybody have to say קדיש
*Kaddish*? Nobody has to say קדיש *Kaddish*? Okay, 9:16. Let's see.
I must have had some chocolate.
Oh, okay. Keep away please.
Alrighty.
All right.
The other day we had a discussion about one of the rabbis
giving a student a hard time, right?
A few days ago.
I'm trying to remember. I wouldn't be surprised, but I'm not recalling.
Rabbi gave a student a hard time? I'm
sure.
We had a discussion about the different lengths of אמות *amos* when
they were talking about making an עירוב *eruv*.
Yeah, we had a discussion about lengths and heights and measuring the
בית המקדש *Beis Hamikdash*. Oh, yeah. And but it was a short
אמה *amah* so it would be like a built-in buffer zone where
they wouldn't be over if they went... Oh,
right.
About the the little extra part of the string, I think you're
talking about, or when they made an עירוב *eruv* they made...
Yeah, but it was an אמה *amah*.
The אמות *amos* were a little shorter. Yeah, yeah, we did have
that too. All right.
But that was a that was a smaller אמה *amah*.